we have main engine start 4 3 2 1 28th
of January 1986 11:39 a.m. the
Challenger space shuttle takes off from
Kennedy Space Center Millions around the
world were watching live as the school
teacher Christa mcff who had been chosen
from 11,000 applicants became the first
civilian passenger of the Space Shuttle
but just 73 seconds into its flight
disaster struck with the world watching
the shuttle exploded tragically killing
everyone on board there were different
rumors about what caused the explosion
but it was months until anyone knew the
facts about what happened there were
four major companies associated with the
shuttle program that were potentially on
the hook Lockheed which managed ground
support Martin Marietta which
manufactured the external fuel tank
Morton thyo which built the booster
rocket and Rockwell International which
built the shuttle and Main engines the
Rogers commission ordered by President
Reagan began investigating the most
famous moment came when Nobel
prizewinning physicist Richard feineman
gave a demonstration showing how the
O-rings used in the solid rocket booster
were catastrophically flawed these were
found to be the points of failure and
after 5 months the conclusion was clear
the fault lay with Morton
thakle in 1998 12 years after the
tragedy the economists Michael Maloney
and Jay Harold mohin published a paper
called called the stock price reaction
to the Challenger crash they set out to
discover the reaction in the stock
market to the companies involved they
said we study an event in which investor
Panic could easily lead to initial
overreaction and because the government
investigation of the cause of the crash
took 5 months one might expect a delayed
stock market reaction to the crash so
how long did they find it took the
market to price in This Disaster days
weeks months it was within 21 minutes
not 21 minutes after the conclusion of
the Rogers commission within 21 minutes
of the explosion itself all four
companies saw an initial drop in their
share price but the three companies that
were not at fault saw much lower volumes
and smaller declines that were more in
line with what was statistically normal
for them on a regular day tho on
the other hand saw huge volumes of
selling by 11:52 a.m. the NYSC halted
trading on Morton th because the order
flow overwhelms their exchange systems
once it continued trading it was down by
6% and by the end of the day it had
dropped 12% there were no signs of
insider trading no information was being
released by the companies involved yet
Morton Thal in the eyes of the market
was clearly singled out to be the
company that was on the hook amazingly
the lasting decline in their market cap
of $200 million was around the same
amount as their eventual damages
settlement and lost future cash flows
this remarkable situation highlights a
powerful phenomenon known as the wisdom
of the crowd The Unbelievable accuracy
that comes from the combined knowledge
analysis and intuition of thousands of
experts motivated by self-interest to
focus on a single objective this
powerful concept is overlooked and
underestimated by most Traders leading
to the biggest mistake that Traders and
investors make when using fundament
mental analysis they confuse having an
opinion with having an opportunity let's
break that down imagine this there's an
fomc meeting coming up so thinking
there's a potential opportunity you
start digging into the financial news
and analyst research after a few hours
you decide that you think it's quite
likely the Federal Reserve will cut
rates and for a further confidence boost
you keep reading that the market
believes there's a 75% chance for rate
cut so the chance for it happen happing
seems to be quite High you connect the
dots lower interest rates means a weeker
dollar so you do your technical analysis
find an entry and short the dollar the
trade is open your confidence is high
because you've backed up your technicals
with fundamentals and now you just have
to wait for the fomc announcement
congratulations you've just made a
mistake why because you only figured out
what you think is going to happen but
not whether it's an opportunity and yet
on social media you'll see Traders is
bragging about this exact approach all
the time I saw the Fed was cutting rates
so I shorted the dollar and made a
profit look how smart I am and the
comments go wild teach me how to trade
fundamentals but what they won't tell
you is this they got lucky and luck is
not a great strategy so here's what's
wrong with that approach one of the
foundational principles of the markets
is that all available information
including information about future
events like an upcoming FC meeting is
reflected in the current price that's a
key idea of the efficient markets
hypothesis and while the EMH has many
flaws this part holds true most of the
time so does the market always get it
right no of course not but as the
Challenger space shuttle example shows
us the Market's collective intelligence
is often far more accurate and far more
impressive than we tend to give it
credit for a lot of Traders like to make
out like the markets are stupid and
they're always getting things wrong as
if they're somehow superior to the
markets as a whole but here's the truth
if you want to profit from fundamentals
or from trading in general you need to
understand this the market is incredibly
intelligent assuming the market is wrong
is just a recipe for disaster it's much
better to always have the position that
the Market's probably right most of the
time so in that case if you're opening a
trade you need to ask yourself what is
it that I'm seeing that thousands of
experts are not but you might might be
thinking yeah but opening a trade
doesn't mean that I'm seeing something
that the market isn't for example
whenever the market is pricing in a rate
cut and then a rate cut does happen you
still see the market reacting to it and
yes that's true but there are a number
of reasons for that a big reason is that
when something's priced in we can think
of it as being priced in as a
probability so for example the 75%
expectation that I referred to in our
example is usually derived from the
markets in the first place
so let me show you what this means with
a simple example let's say that we're
analyzing an asset that's currently
priced at $100 but then suddenly out of
the blue there's an economic event
that's announced that's one week away
and there are two possible outcomes of
that event outcome a or outcome B if
outcome a happens the asset will be
repriced to
$110 if outcome B happens the asset will
stay at $100 because it means there's no
change to the underlying value now if
before the event the price actually
starts drifting up and it reaches
$107.50 with all else being equal we
might say that now what's being priced
in is a 75% chance of outcome a so from
this point onwards there's a 75% chance
of a further gain of
$2.50 and a 25% chance of a loss of
$7.50 so if you as the trader also
agreed that the probability was 75% and
so you decided decided to enter a long
trade you'd have no Edge at all your
probability estimate is aligned with the
base rate now the chances are for this
individual trade you will make a $250
profit because there's a 75% chance of
that happening but if you trade like
this over and over again over time
you'll just end up at break even because
you have no Edge so what now does this
mean I'm saying we should just give up
on fundamental analysis no not at all in
fact some of my biggest trades
life-changing ones have come as a result
of fundamentals and then finding the
entry point with technicals but the
thing is to profit from fundamental
analysis you need to understand what
creates an opportunity in the first
place and I believe there are three
broad ways having information no one
else has having rare expertise in the
relevant area or having a better
estimate of probabilities now let me
save you some time Gordon gecko the
first option isn't viable unless you
enjoy spending time behind buz why
because it's called insider trading and
it's illegal unless of course you're a
member of Congress the next option is to
be among a small minority of experts in
a relevant field so imagine this you're
the world's leading expert on lithium
hexif Flor phosphate that is a bit of a
mouthful to say it's a compound that's
used in lithium ion batteries one day a
car manufacturer announces a
revolutionary new electric car with
record-breaking battery life using that
particular compound they've discovered
this secret and the market goes wild and
the stock price SS but you the world
leading expert know something that the
rest of the market doesn't know you know
that this particular compound degrades
rapidly in cold weather not only because
you've seen the tests but because you
were the person who ran the tests you
crunch the numbers you know that
failures and recalls are inevitable so
while the market Buys in into the hype
you start shorting the stock the result
massive profits but just like the market
in that example let's get ourselves
firmly back to reality building this
level of expertise takes years if not
decades and it's going to be limited to
specific niches most Traders don't have
and will never have that kind of edge or
the opportunity to use it so that brings
us on to the final and most practical
way to find Opportunities with
fundamental analysis which is have
better probability estimates than the
market so let's go back to our example
if the market has priced in a 75%
probability we can call that the base
rate so the base rate is a 75% chance of
a $250 move and a 25% chance of a $750
move that's Break Even but you've done
extensive research you've analyzed all
the data you've watched all the speeches
of people involved in the event and used
AI to pick up on body language nuances
and you're very very sure the
probabilities are actually a 60% chance
of outcome a and a 40% chance of outcome
B so your probabilities are different to
what's currently priced in you agree
with the market that outcome a is more
likely but the viable trade for you
right now is to go short rather than
going long why because if your
probabilities are right it means the
market is mispricing the event so by
going short it means you have a 40%
probability of a $750 profit and a 60%
probability of a $250 loss meaning the
expectancy would be
$150 so in this situation if you just
did what most Traders do and thought to
yourself okay it's likely to be outcome
a so I should go long without even
realizing it you would have been taking
a negative expectancy trade if you keep
taking trades like that over and over
again over time you're going to lose
money it's only by quantifying your
prediction about what you think is going
to happen and explicitly stating the
probabilities that you would have
realized that the market has gone too
far in pricing in the event and the
opportunity is to be contrarian you see
the wisdom of crowds is amazing over
time across all these different events
and all these things that take place on
average the market will get it right
some of those times will be remarkable
uncannily accurate predictions like the
Challenger disaster but also part of the
average will be times where it isn't
accurate at all so when you do your
analysis and quantify your conclusions
you might decide you're not confident
enough to go against what the market
suggests or you might see that your
expectation matches what's already
priced in but every now and then you'll
pick up on something that you think the
market hasn't got quite right and those
opportunities can be absolutely huge if
you want to understand more about this
way of approaching things in the markets
which I honestly believe is the most
professional and most Dependable way
check out the free trading that's Linked
In the description box that goes into
much more detail for both technical
analysis and fundamental analysis or
watch one of these videos that are
linked on screen next that will help
improve your trading dramatically by
starting to use probabilities